<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5905 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7821 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7821.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7822 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7822.xml">
<!ENTITY NTS SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ntp-using-nts-for-ntp.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-mlichvar-ntp-correction-field-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>NTP Correction Field</title>

    <author fullname="Miroslav Lichvar" initials="M." surname="Lichvar">
      <organization>Red Hat</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Purkynova 115</street>
          <city>Brno</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>612 00</code>
          <country>Czech Republic</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mlichvar@redhat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2017" month="October" day="30"/>

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>NTP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies an extension field for the Network Time
        Protocol (NTP) which allows network devices such as switches and
        routers to modify NTP packets with corrections to improve accuracy
        of the synchronization in the network.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Processing and queueing delays in network switches and routers may be
        a significant source of jitter and asymmetry in network delay, which
        has a negative impact on accuracy and stability of synchronization of
        clocks in local networks using <xref target="RFC5905">NTP</xref>.</t>

      <t>If all network devices on the paths between NTP clients and servers
        implemented NTP and supported an operation as a server and client, the
        impact of the delays could be avoided by configuring NTP to make
        measurements only between devices and hosts that are directly connected
        to one another. In the <xref target="IEEE1588">Precision Time Protocol
          (PTP)</xref>, which is a different protocol for synchronization of
        clocks in networks, such devices would be called Boundary Clocks
        (BC).</t>

      <t>A different approach supported by PTP to improve the accuracy uses
        Transparent Clocks (TC). Instead of fully implementing PTP in order to
        support an operation as a BC, the devices only modify a correction
        field in forwarded PTP packets with the time that the packets had to
        wait for transmission. The final value of the correction is included in
        the calculation of the delay and offset, which may significantly
        improve the accuracy and stability of the synchronization.</t>

      <t>This document describes an NTP extension field which allows the
        devices to make similar correction in forwarded NTP packets.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
          document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
            target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Format of Correction Field">
      <t>The Correction Field is an NTP extension field following <xref
          target="RFC7822">RFC 7822</xref>. The format of the extension field
        is shown in Figure <xref format="counter"
          target="correction-field-format"></xref>.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="correction-field-format"
          title="Format of Correction Field">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          Field Type           |          Length (28)          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Receive Correction       |      Transmit Correction      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                       Origin Correction                       |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                        Delay Correction                       |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Origin ID   |    Path ID    |     Checksum complement       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The extension field has the following fields:</t>

      <t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Field Type"><vspace/>
            The type which identifies the Correction extension field. TBD</t>

          <t hangText="Length"><vspace/>
            The length of the extension field, which is 28 octets.</t>

          <t hangText="Receive Correction"><vspace/>
            A 16-bit extension of the receive timestamp in the NTP header
            increasing its resolution. The extended receive timestamp has 32
            integer bits and 48 fractional bits.</t>

          <t hangText="Transmit Correction"><vspace/>
            A 16-bit extension of the transmit timestamp in the NTP header
            increasing its resolution. The extended transmit timestamp has 32
            integer bits and 48 fractional bits.</t>

          <t hangText="Origin Correction"><vspace/>
            A field which contains a copy of the final delay correction from
            the previous packet in the NTP exchange.</t>

          <t hangText="Delay Correction"><vspace/>
            A signed fixed-point number of seconds with 16 integer bits and 48
            fractional bits, which represents the current correction of the
            network delay that has accumulated for this packet on the path from
            the source to the destination.</t>

          <t hangText="Origin ID"><vspace/>
            A field which contains a copy of the final path ID from the
            previous packet in the NTP exchange.</t>

          <t hangText="Path ID"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit identification number of the path where the delay
            correction was updated.</t>

          <t hangText="Checksum Complement"><vspace/>
            A field which can be modified to not change the UDP checksum after
            updating the other fields. The same field is described in <xref
              target="RFC7821">RFC 7821</xref>.</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Network devices">
      <t>A network device which is forwarding a packet and supports the
        Correction Field MUST NOT modify the packet unless all of the following
        applies:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>The packet is an IPv4 or IPv6 UDP packet.</t>
          <t>The source port or destination port is 123.</t>
          <t>The NTP version is 4.</t>
          <t>The NTP mode is 1, 2, 3, 4, or 5.</t>
          <t>The format of the packet is valid per RFC 7822.</t>
          <t>The packet contains an extension field which has a type of TBD and
            length of 28 octets.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>The device SHOULD add to the current value in the delay correction
        field the length of an interval between the reception and transmission
        of the packet. If the packet is transmitted at the same speed as it was
        received and the length of the packet does not change (e.g. due to
        adding or removing a VLAN tag), the beginning and end of the interval
        may correspond to any point of the reception and transmission as long
        as it is consistent for all forwarded packets of the same length. If
        the transmission speed or length of the packet is different, the
        beginning and end of the interval SHOULD correspond to the end of the
        reception and beginning of the transmission respectively.</t>

      <t>If the transmission starts before the reception ends, a negative value
        may need to be added to the delay correction. The end of the reception
        SHOULD be determined using the length field of the UDP header and the
        speed at which the packet is received.</t>

      <t>If the device updates the delay correction, it SHOULD also add the
        identification numbers of the incoming and outgoing port to the path
        ID.</t>

      <t>If the device modified any field of the extension field, it MUST
        update the checksum complement field in order to keep the current UDP
        checksum valid, or update the UDP checksum itself.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="NTP hosts">
      <t>When an NTP client sends a request to a server and the association is
        configured to use the Correction Field, it SHOULD add the extension
        field to the packet. All fields of the extension field except type and
        length SHOULD be set to zero.</t>

      <t>When the server receives a packet which includes the extension field,
        the response SHOULD also include the extension field.</t>

      <t>If the server's clock has a better precision than resolution of the
        64-bit NTP timestamp format, the server SHOULD save the additional bits
        in the receive and transmit correction fields and set the precision
        field to the corresponding number, which is smaller than -32.
        Otherwise, the receive and transmit correction fields SHOULD be
        zero.</t>

      <t>The origin correction and origin ID fields SHOULD be set to the delay
        correction and path ID from the request. The other fields of the
        Correction Field SHOULD be zero.</t>

      <t>When the client receives a response which contains the extension
        field, it SHOULD check the value of both the origin and delay
        correction fields. If a correction is larger than a specified maximum
        (e.g. 1 second), the extension field SHOULD be ignored.</t>

      <t>The client MAY log a warning if the origin ID and path ID are not
        equal, which indicates the network path between the server and client
        is not symmetric.</t>

      <t>If the client's clock has a better precision than resolution of the
        64-bit NTP format and the precision field in the response contains a
        number smaller than -32, the client SHOULD extend the receive and
        transmit timestamp from the NTP header with the additional bits from
        the receive and transmit correction fields respectively.</t>

      <t>When the client computes the offset and delay using the formulas from
        RFC 5905, the origin correction is subtracted from the receive
        timestamp and the delay correction is added to the transmit
        timestamp.</t>

      <t>An NTP peer follows the rules of both servers and clients. It
        processes Correction Fields in received packets as a client and sends
        Correction Fields as a server. A packet which has a zero origin
        timestamp (i.e. it is not a response to a request) SHOULD have a zero
        origin correction and zero origin ID in the Correction Field.
      </t>

      <t>A broadcast server using the Correction Field SHOULD always set the
        origin correction and origin ID fields to zero.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The Correction Field extension is based on the PTP correction field
        specified in IEEE 1588-2008.</t>

      <t>The author would like to thank Tal Mizrahi for his useful
        comments.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to allocate an Extension Field Type for the
        Correction Field.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>NTP packets including the Correction Field cannot be authenticated
        by a legacy MAC, because the MAC has to cover all extension fields in
        the packet and devices which are supposed to modify the field are not
        able to update the MAC.</t>

      <t>It is recommended to authenticate NTP packets using an authentication
        extension field, e.g. the <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-ntp-using-nts-for-ntp">NTS Authenticator and
          Encrypted Extensions</xref> extension field, and add the Correction
        Field to the packet after the authentication field.</t>

      <t>A man-in-the-middle attacker can delay packets in the network in order
        to increase the measured delay and shift the measured offset by up to
        half of the extra delay. If the packets contain the Correction Field,
        the attacker can reduce the delay calculated by the client or peer and
        shift the offset even more. The maximum correction should be limited
        (e.g. to 1 second) to prevent the attacker from injecting a larger
        offset to the measurements.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;

      &RFC5905;

      &RFC7822;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="IEEE1588">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Standard for a Precision Clock Synchronization Protocol
            for Networked Measurement and Control Systems</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IEEE std. 1588-2008</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2008"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      &RFC7821;

      &NTS;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
